Edward C. Blomeyer photographic collection, Inclusive: 1906-1923, Bulk: 1912-1920
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Edward C. Blomeyer photographic collection
Inclusive: 1906-1923, Bulk: 1912-1920
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3886
E.C. Blomeyer, 1906-1923
Over 1,500 photographic materials including Texas, Missouri, Illinois, Arkansas, North Carolina, Colorado, and Canada. The images were taken from approximately 1906-1923.
The Edward C. Blomeyer photographic collection contains photos from circa 1906 to 1923, including of the early telephone industry in Missouri and Texas, locations in Waco, and events such as the Texas Cotton Palace exhibition and parade. Blomeyer was president of the Texas Telephone Company.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Edward Charles (E.C) Blomeyer was born in Missouri in 1882. He married Amma Pottinger in 1904 and together they had three children, Mary, Edward, and Earle. During his time in Waco, Texas, 1912-1920, Mr. Blowmeyer became one of the early pioneers in the telephone industry in central Texas. He served in many capacities in this growing field, helping to establish and improve communication networks throughout the central Texas area. As well as his work in the telephone industry, he was active in community service in the Waco area. Examples include membership in the following organizations: the Young Men's Business League (YMBL), in which he served as chairman, Waco Chamber of Commerce, Waco Ad Club, Waco Public Library, and the Waco Rotary Club. He was also a member of the Karem Temple and various Masonic organizations in the city. Additionally, his two sons were born in Waco.
In 1904, Blomeyer entered the telephone industry working for the Southeast Missouri Telephone Company, in Charleston, Missouri, starting as auditor, then secretary, and later its manager. In 1912, he moved to Waco, Texas, to work for the Brazos Valley Telegraph and Telephone Company. In 1914, the Texas Telephone Company merged with 5 separate telephone companies in central, south, and east Texas. This conglomeration expanded the Texas Telephone Company greatly operating lines through thirty-four towns in the state at that time.
Blomeyer first served as secretary-treasurer of the newly formed Texas Telephone Company, as well as assistant to the president, J.B. (John Baylis) Earle II. The Texas Telephone Company's local expansion included Lorena, Mart, McGregor, Moody, Waco, and West, Texas. In 1918, E.C. Blomeyer became president of the TTC as the company continued to buy out or merge with several other independent telephone operations in the greater central Texas area. Additionally, in 1918, he began serving as president of the Texas Independent Telephone Association, a position he held until 1920; he would later be designated an honorary life member. Serving in this capacity he took part in proceedings, and later, executive positions in the United States Independent Telephone Association.
E.C. Blomeyer's time in Waco and the central Texas area helped build on his previous experience in the telephone industry. As a result, in 1920, he took a position with the Automatic Electric Company, owned by Theodore Gary and Co., of Chicago, Illinois. The AEC of Chicago's corporate lineage began in the Strowger Automatic Telephone Exchange Co., started by the inventor of the dial telephone, Almon Strowger. AEC bought the patents from Strowger in 1918 and was a major supplier of dial-telephones to independent telephone companies in the United States and abroad. Blomeyer's arrival at Automatic Electric was at an important time in that company's history. The Strowger (rotary-dial telephone) patents which they held had just been licensed to the Bell Corporation for a sum of $2.5 million. After the sale, AEC still continued to produce the rotary-dial system for telephone operations other than the Bell Corporation.
In his position at the Automatic Electric Company, Blomeyer also served as contract sales manager for its associated company, the International Telephone Sales and Engineering Corporation. In doing so, he supervised overseas business and contract sales of dial telephones. At this time, the AEC manufactured and supplied approximately 80 percent of the automatic dial-operated telephone equipment used worldwide. In 1923, he was made vice-president of Theodore Gary and Co., owner of the AEC, and remained so until his retirement in 1956. The Theodore Gary & Co., was later purchased by General Telephone Corporation in 1955, later renamed General Telephone & Electronics (GTE).
With his keen interest in the telephone industry and engineering, Blomeyer was also a prolific writer contributing articles to several publications including: The Magazine of Business; Telephony: The American Telephone Journal; Business, A Magazine for Office Store, and Factory; Public Utilities Fortnightly; American Telephone Journal, and Popular Mechanics. He was also known throughout the telephone industry as the author of a series of booklets entitled: Letters to Managers. By 1934, copies of the ten book series numbered over three million in circulation.
After retirement, he spent some of his remaining years in Palm Beach, Florida, where he died in 1964. A year later, to recognize his life's work in the telephone industry, E.C. Blomeyer was inducted into the Independent Telephone Hall of Fame. Additionally, the Blomeyer's were a philanthropic family and shared the benefits of their success. The widow of Edward Charles Blowmeyer, Amma, donated funds to Palm Beach Atlantic College enabling the establishment of the E.C. Blomeyer Library, dedicated on March 9, 1969. The library is now called the Warren Library (dedicated 2007) as a series of donations has enabled Palm Beach Atlantic University to expand since its beginning in 1968. E.C. Blomeyer's legacy carries on as a benefactor of this university, in his writings, photographic record, and contributions to the telephone industry, including that of central Texas.
Scope and Content
The Edward C. Blomeyer photographic collection consists of photo negatives and prints taken by Edward Charles Blomeyer, a pioneer in the telephone industry. His photographic record gives an insight into the early telephone and communications networks of the central Texas area. Additionally, while living in Waco, he photographed the city including popular sites such as Cameron Park and events such as The Texas Cotton Palace. Structures such as many of the city's famous bridges are recorded and events such as auto races are represented. The collection also includes images of early road conditions and scenes around McLennan County, Texas.
Outside of Waco, Blomeyer took images including San Antonio, Austin, and the Texas gulf coast. His vacations were recorded as well, including Yellowstone National Park and Bella Vista, Arkansas. Also photographed are ships, autos, airplanes, people-including family members, and his home state of Missouri.
Arrangement
E.C. Blomeyer organized the photo negatives and prints in this collection by subject using an index card box with small folders separated by divider tabs. The general arrangement remained intact as when the collection was received. It did require some reconciliation of misfiled items and renaming of subjects/series for better identification purposes. The Edward C. Blomeyer photographic collection is now arranged in eight series: I. Company: Telephone, II. Texas, III. Vacation, IV. People, V. Missouri, VI. Transportation, VII. Agriculture, and VIII. General.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3886. Acquired 2012-06-28
Related Resources
Related references
"Biographical and Personal Notes." Telephony: American Telephone Journal 79, no. 4 (1920 July 24): 32-34. Accessed 2013 December 23.
Blomeyer, Edward Charles. "Convention of Texas Independent Telephone Association." Telephony: American Telephone Journal 67, no. 20 (1914 November 14): 22-24 [54-56]. Accessed 2013 December 23.
Blomeyer, Edward Charles. "Still Now Heads Texas Association." Telephony: American Telephone Journal 79, no. 4 (1920 July 24): 14-15. Accessed 2013 December 23.
The Electronic Encyclopedia of Chicago: "Automatic Electric Co." Accessed 2013 December 23.
"From Factory and Salesroom." Telephony: American Telephone Journal 80, no.17 (1921 April 23): 40, 42. Accessed 2013 December 23.
MacMeal, Harry B. The Story of Independent Telephony. Chicago: Independent Pioneer Telephone Association, 1934. Accessed 2013 December 23.
"Texas Telephone Co., Waco, Texas." Standard Corporation Service, Daily Revised 1, (1914 May 1-December 31): 260. Accessed 2013 December 23.
Wright, Todd. "Mrs. Blomeyer to be Honored at Dedication of PBAC Library." Palm Beach Post (Palm Beach, FL), 1969 February 27.
Index Terms
Places
McLennan County (Tex.) -- History.; Ranches -- Texas -- History.; Rich Field (Waco, Tex.); Texas -- History.; Waco (Tex.) -- History -- 20th Century.
Subjects
Aeronautics -- History.; Aeronautics, Military -- United States -- History.; Alamo (San Antonio, Tex.); Architecture, Industrial -- Texas -- History.; Automobiles -- History.; Brazos River (Tex.) -- History.; Bridges -- Texas -- Waco.; Cameron Park (Waco, Tex.) -- History.; Camp MacArthur (Tex.); Cotton -- Texas -- Waco -- Exhibitions.; Cotton Belt Railway.; Eastland (Ship); Floods -- Texas -- History.; Galveston (Tex.) -- History.; Military bases -- Texas -- Waco.; Military training camps -- Texas -- Waco.; Missouri -- History.; Oil wells -- Texas -- History.; Railroad accidents -- Texas.; Railroads -- Texas -- History.; Railroads -- United States -- History.; Roads -- Texas.; Ships -- History.; St. Louis Southwestern Railway Lines.; Steam -- navigation -- Mississippi river.; Telecommunication -- Texas.; Telephone -- History.; Telephone -- Private branch exchanges.; Telephone -- United States.; Telephone companies -- Texas.; Texas Cotton Palace Exposition (Waco, Tex.); Waco Suspension Bridge (Waco, Tex.); Wilderness areas -- Arkansas.; Women -- Employment -- United States -- History -- 20th century.
Genres
Cellulose negative; Photographic print; Photographs.
- Company: Telephone, 1906-1920; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  In 1904, E.C. Blomeyer entered the telephone industry working for the Southeast Missouri Telephone Company, in Charleston, Missouri. The images in this series include industry related subjects beginning in the states of Missouri and Illinois. Blomeyer then moved to Waco, Texas, in 1912, to work for the Brazos Valley Telegraph and Telephone Company, and later The Texas Telephone Company after a large merger of many independent telephone entities.
  The merging expanded operations of the Texas Telephone Company to Lorena, Mart, McGregor, Moody, and West, Texas. By 1918, E.C. Blomeyer had become president of the TTC and the company continued to buy out or merge with several other telephone operations around the state. The images in this series help document the work done after these acquisitions. In some cases, telephone poles, lines, and equipment were primitive or outdated for their time, and they are detailed in these photographs.
  - Missouri and Illinois, 1906-1912; 1
    This subseries of images includes buildings, office spaces, switch board operators, equipment, and people from the Southeast Missouri Telephone Company. Most are believed to be in or around Charleston, Missouri, although some locations include telephone exchanges in Illinois. These images by E.C. Blomeyer date from approximately 1906 to circa 1912.
    - Missouri and Illinois, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 5)
    - Missouri and Illinois: MO or ILL. Telephone Building, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 6)
    - Missouri and Illinois: Man Climbing Pole, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 7)
    - Missouri and Illinois 922-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-922.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 8)
    - Missouri and Illinois: “Banner Exchange, Best Record in Toll Ticket Work.”, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 9)
    - Missouri and Illinois 689-2: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-689.2.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 10)
    - Missouri and Illinois 690-2: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-690.2.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 11)
    - Missouri and Illinois, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 12)
    - Missouri and Illinois 690-3: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-690.3.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 13)
    - Missouri and Illinois 809-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-809.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 14)
    - Missouri and Illinois 905-11: Southeast Missouri Telephone Co. Building-Interior: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-905.11.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 15)
    - Missouri and Illinois 809-2: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-809.2.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 16)
    - Missouri and Illinois 784-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-784.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 17)
    - Missouri and Illinois 778-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-778.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 18)
    - Missouri and Illinois: Personnel 775-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-775.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 19)
    - Missouri and Illinois: Man on Pole, Church in Background 775-2: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-775.2.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 20)
    - Missouri and Illinois 755-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-755.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 21)
    - Missouri and Illinois 782: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-comp-tele-moill-782.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 22)
    - Missouri and Illinois: Street Scene-Poles and Lines, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 23)
  - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio, 1906-1920; 2
    Description of Material
    This subseries consists of images of telephone company buildings and related subjects in Texas. Examples include the Brazos Valley Telegraph and Telephone Company in Oglesby, Texas Telephone Company in Waco, and company operations in San Antonio. Also included are interior views of telephone buildings with switchboard operators and office spaces.
    Electronic Resources
    Collection Files
    Telephone Building: The Texas Telephone Company headquarters, located at 119 North 9th Street, Waco, Texas. This image was taken from the "garden roof-top" of the building. E.C. Blomeyer worked for and later became president of this company. The digital image is taken from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-796.1.tif. Photo taken by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1918.
    San Antonio: This picture was taken in office space in the San Antonio, Texas, branch of the Southwestern Telegraph and Telephone Company. The digital image is from a scan of a 4 by 3 ¼- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-923.3.tif. Photo taken by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1906.
    Telephone Building: The Texas Telephone Company headquarters, located at 119 North 9th Street, Waco, Texas. E.C. Blomeyer worked for and later became president of this company. The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-762.2.tif. Photo taken by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1918.
    Pictured is an early telephone booth of The Texas Telephone Company. "The sign reads: "The Texas Telephone Company, First on the Ground." The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-512.2.tif. Picture taken by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1918.
    Telephone Building: The Texas Telephone Company headquarters, located at 119 North 9th Street, Waco, Texas. This image was taken from the "garden roof-top" of the building. The Amicable (Alico) Building is seen in the distance. E.C. Blomeyer worked for and later became president of this company. The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-785.1.tif. Photo taken by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1918.
    Telephone Building: The Texas Telephone Company headquarters, located at 119 North 9th Street, Waco, Texas. E.C. Blomeyer worked for and later became president of this company. The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-497.2.tif. Photo taken by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1918.
    San Antonio: This picture was taken in office space in the San Antonio, Texas, branch of the Southwestern Telegraph and Telephone Company. The digital image is from a scan of a 4 by 3 ¼- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-754.1.tif. Photo taken by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1906.
    This image is of two switchboard operators working at the Moody, Texas, branch of the Brazos Valley Telegraph and Telephone Company, owned by the Texas Telephone Company. The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-512.1.tif. The picture is dated August 8, 1917. Photo taken by E.C. Blomeyer.
    Telephone Building: The Texas Telephone Company headquarters, located at 119 North 9th Street, Waco, Texas. E.C. Blomeyer worked for and later became president of this company. The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-758.2.tif. Photo taken by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1918.
    E.C. Blomeyer worked for the Brazos Valley Telegraph and Telephone Company, where he served as auditor, then secretary-treasurer. Shown is one of their buildings in Oglesby, Texas. This picture is dated August 8, 1917. The digital image is taken from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-wctsa-756.2.tif. Photo taken by E.C. Blomeyer.
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco-Flood Aftermath 753-3: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-753.3.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 24)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco 762-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-762.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 25)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco 762-2: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-762.2.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 26)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco-Telephone Building 758-2: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-758.2.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 27)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco-Telephone Building 497-2: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-497.2.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 28)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco-Telephone Building, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 29)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco-Telephone Building 796-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-796.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 30)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco-Telephone Building 785-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-785.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 31)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco 756-2: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-756.2.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 32)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Moody 512-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-512.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 33)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Waco-TTC Phone Booth 512.2: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-512.2.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 34)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: Oglesby 757-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-757.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 35)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: San Antonio 754-1: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-754.1.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 36)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio: San Antonio 923-3: Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer 3886-wctsa-923.3.tif, 1906-1920 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 37)
    - Waco, Central Texas, and San Antonio, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Telephone Poles, Lines, and Equipment, 1912-1920
      This subseries contains rural telephone poles and lines documented by E.C. Blomeyer. They help show the primitive way in which equipment used for telecommunications was constructed in the early days of this industry in McLennan County, Texas, and surrounding counties. Additionally, storage facilities are included showing a detailed look at early telephones and equipment.
      Poles and lines: These telephone poles are located on the McGregor Road on the outskirts of Waco, Texas. The Amicable (Alico) Building can be seen in the distance. The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-ple-509.2.tif. Photo by E.C. Blomeyer, March 3, 1918.
      Equipment: The image shows a Texas Telephone Company repair and storage facility. The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 4 inch, photo print. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-ple-513.2.tif. Picture by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1917, McLennan County, Texas.
      Poles and lines: E.C. Blomeyer's note on the back of the printed version of this photograph states: "Connections or 'joints' made by the former owners [prior to Texas Telephone Company buyout] in their telephone lines." The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-ple-757.3.tif. Photo by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1917, in McLennan County, Texas, or the greater area.
      Poles and lines: E.C. Blomeyer's note on the back of the printed version of this photograph states: "A rural telephone pole." The digital image is from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-ple-758.1.tif. Photo by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1916, in McLennan County, Texas, or the greater area.
      Poles and lines: In the picture an array of makeshift poles hold telephone wire that's not securely connected. The digital image is from a scan of a 1 ¾ by 2 ¾- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-ple-952.3.tif. Photo by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1916, in McLennan County, Texas, or the greater area.
      Poles and lines: This picture shows how telephone lines were ones held by makeshift poles attached to barbed wire fences. The digital image is from a scan of a 1 ¾ by 2 ¾- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-ple-952.2.tif. Photo by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1916, in McLennan County, Texas, or the greater area.
      Poles and lines: These telephone poles are located on the outskirts of Waco, Texas. The digital image is taken from a scan of a 6 by 3 ½- inch, cellulose nitrate negative. Digital ID: tx-phoarch-blomeyer_3886-ple-785.3.tif. Photo by E.C. Blomeyer, circa 1916.